Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, we have the final episode
in our series on Ozempic
and we ask what’s a safer and cheaper
way to lose weight than GLP-1 drugs?
Can we drug our way
out of the obesity crisis?
Are these GLP-1 drugs the answer
to the obesity epidemic?
The head of
the European Association
for the Study of Obesity
was pretty bullish,
conveniently failing to disclose
that his group had received
millions of dollars
from the drug maker.
But doesn’t getting
a tiny weekly injection
sound far easier than getting
all sweaty in the gym?
Do these game-changing
new medications
"make lifestyle-based treatment
of obesity obsolete"?
Let’s ask those paid by
the two main GLP-1 drug makers,
which now have
a combined net worth
greater than a trillion dollars.
The World Obesity Federation,
which evidently just got
a million dollars
from the Ozempic company,
published a consensus statement
in one of its journals
favoring the definition
of obesity as a disease.
This designation
may not benefit patients,
but it will benefit doctors
and drug companies
when health insurance
and clinical guidelines
promote treatment
with drugs and surgery.
A concern is that labeling
obesity as a disease
risks reducing our autonomy,
disempowering and robbing us
of the intrinsic motivation
that’s an important enabler
of change.
It encourages fatalism,
promoting the fallacy
that genetics are destiny.
But, of course,
it can’t be our genes.
The obesity epidemic only
started a few decades ago.
Our genes didn’t somehow
magically change
in the late 1970s.
Others blame lack of willpower,
but that doesn’t make
any sense either.
All of us coincidentally lost
our collective self-control?
It’s the food.
The rise in the number
of excess calories
provided by the U.S. food supply
is more than sufficient
to explain the obesity epidemic.
Obesity is not
some moral failing.
The battle of the bulge is
a battle against biology.
We’re living
in a toxic food environment,
drowning in a sea
of excess calories,
being bombarded with ads
for fast food and candy.
Becoming overweight is
a normal, natural response
to the abnormal,
unnatural ubiquity
of sugary, fatty foods that are
concentrated with calories.
So, the prime cause
for the obesity epidemic
is neither gluttony nor sloth.
Being overweight may simply be
a normal response,
by normal people,
to an abnormal situation.
And with nearly three-quarters
of Americans overweight,
it’s literally normal.
So, if obesity is
to be understood
as "normal physiology within
a pathological environment,"
there is an argument
that drugs like Ozempic
really aren’t tackling
the root cause of obesity.
These drugs will likely have
only a modest effect
on reducing
the rapidly growing epidemic
and may even make it worse,
as Big Pharma and its lobbyists
try to shift society’s focus
to drugs
rather than broader
public health strategies.
The real solution would involve
fixing the food system,
but why would Big Food
change its ways
if obesity can be treated
with drugs?
So, the main actors responsible
for creating and perpetuating
the obesity-generating world
will continue undisturbed.
England’s health secretary
was keen to use GLP-1 drugs
as a "way of preventing illness
without resorting
to ’nanny state’ measures,"
but advocates are just
talking about things like
restricting the thousands of ads
kids see every year
for candy, liquid candy
(soft drinks),
breakfast candy, and fast food.
A quarter century ago,
the term "Social Determinants
of Health" was coined,
defined as the nonmedical
factors that influence health
too often ignored
by the medical establishment,
such as poverty.
They explain why the top
1 percent, for example,
live about 10 to 15 years longer
than the bottom 1 percent.
More recently,
based on experience
with the alcohol
and tobacco industries,
the concept of "Commercial
Determinants of Health"
was introduced,
which can be defined as
"factors that influence health
which stem from the profit
motive," also referred to
as the Corporate
Determinants of Health.
The food and beverage sectors
spend huge amounts
on developing
and marketing products
packed with sugar,
fat, and salt,
deliberately designed
to lead to addictive consumption
that contributes
to the increasing prevalence
of chronic disease.
Public corporations like
Coca-Cola have a legal duty
to maximize return
to their shareholders,
and those running the companies
are heavily incentivized
to achieve this.
Many observers are outraged
by stories
of what some of these companies
do to maximize returns,
but as people working in the
tobacco industry can testify,
being the subject
of widespread disrepute
is more than offset
by the financial rewards.
And psychological defense
mechanisms can take care
of any residual unease about
contributing to the suffering
and death of fellow humans whom
they do not personally know.
The greatest challenge
to improving health may lie
in the tension between
wealth creation
and health creation.
Introducing a temporary
weight-loss fix
using GLP-1 drugs like Ozempic,
without consideration
of their wider implications
and a long-term plan,
has been likened to sprinkling
water on a raging blaze.
The war against obesity
cannot be won without measures
to prevent obesity
in the first place.
That means tackling
the food environment,
which is based on high-calorie,
fatty, salty, sugary junk,
rather than relying
on medication
as a "damage limitation
exercise."
Yeah, but limiting damage
is a good thing.
Sure, these drugs may not make
much of a dent
on a population scale,
but what about
on an individual basis?
It’d be great if people ate
healthfully enough
to prevent and treat
heart disease,
high blood pressure,
and diabetes too,
but until that happens,
drugs for those conditions
can literally be life saving.
Obesity so dramatically
decreases one’s lifespan--
reducing life expectancy
as much as a decade--
that these GLP-1 drugs--
like bariatric surgery--
should be considered
as a last resort
for those unwilling
or unable to treat
the cause of their obesity.
Put diabetics on Ozempic,
and they eat less
high-fat and sweet foods.
Put nondiabetics on Ozempic,
and they eat less high-fat
and non-sweet foods.
So, diabetics on Ozempic
are eating fewer
pastries and doughnuts,
and nondiabetics on Ozempic
are eating fewer ham, cheese,
and sausage sandwiches.
The problem
is people eat too much crap;
so, anything that gets people
to eat less crap
can be beneficial,
including surgically rearranging
our digestive organs
with bariatric surgery.
But we don’t need
to go under the knife
or take a $1,000-a-month drug
to de-crap our diet.
But what about the cravings,
though?
The obesogenic environment--
that is, the obesity-generating
toxic food environment--
can overwhelm
even substantial efforts
to enact individual
behavioral changes.
After ramping up for three
months to high-dose Ozempic,
people are able
to cut nearly 1,000 calories
out of their daily diet.
How could you possibly do that
without drugs,
unless you were on some kind
of liquid diet
meal-replacement shakes
or something?
Or, you could eat
a diet centered around
the healthiest foods
on the planet.
If you put people on a diet
packed with fruits, vegetables,
whole grains, and beans,
and allow them to eat
as much as they want,
they end up eating about
50 percent fewer calories
than they might have otherwise.
Just as full,
on half the calories.
Wait. How can people be
satisfied after cutting
more than 1,000 calories
out of their daily diets?
By eating more high-bulk,
low-calorie-density foods
(vegetables, fruits,
whole grains, and beans)
and fewer calorie-dense foods,
like meats, cheeses,
sugars, and fats.
No wonder a whole food
plant-based diet apparently
achieved greater weight loss
than any other diet.
So, could good nutrition present
a safer and cheaper approach
to weight loss
for most patients?
Not only can the ingestion
of a plant-based meal
more than double
GLP-1 secretion,
compared to
a same-calorie meat meal,
but plant-based diets
can also cause weight loss
by virtue of calorie-trapping,
high-fiber foods,
which flush calories away,
or by boosting
our resting metabolic rate,
which helps explain
why the largest study
of vegans to date
showed that those eating
strictly plant-based diets
are about 35 pounds (16 kg)
lighter, on average.
One randomized trial found
that a strictly plant-based diet
may reduce annual food costs
by about $500.
Healthier, more plant-based,
diets may be about
25 percent less expensive.
And eating groats and greens,
maybe even spicy
groats and greens,
may be able to provide
an extra GLP-1 boost.
For more healthy
weight-loss tips,
check out my evidence-based
weight-loss book,
for which all proceeds I receive
are donated to charity.
The Drug and Therapeutics
Bulletin,
which is also independent
and doesn’t accept
any advertising,
concluded that more data
on Ozempic’s
long-term safety and efficacy
are needed
before it can be recommended
for routine use
for the treatment of obesity,
reminding readers
that historically,
nearly all the drugs
approved for weight loss
have later been
pulled from the market
because of safety concerns.
But wait.
Obesity so dramatically
decreases one’s lifespan
that even if these drugs
ended up shaving years
off of people’s lives,
wouldn’t they still be worth it?
Well, that assumes
these drugs cure obesity,
but if you remember from
the drug’s own package insert,
in all the major trials,
people started out obese
and ended up obese,
after the drugs effectively
stopped working
and body weight plateaus.
Then, you’re paying to take the
drug for the rest of your life
just so you don’t lose ground
and re-gain everything,
while continuing to face any
and all long-term side effects.
Historically, the medical
profession has offered
a sorry collection of harmful
or downright dangerous
weight-loss interventions.
Caution about
long-term side effects is,
therefore, warranted.
If you look at
the post-approval withdrawal
of anti-obesity drugs,
pulled from the market
because of safety concerns
only discovered years later,
it took an average of a decade
before dangers came to light,
and in one case,
we didn’t discover
a weight-loss drug’s
long-term adverse effects
until 38 years
after it hit the market.
What’s more, even after
that first report of danger,
it takes an average
of another decade
to actually get it banned.
It can even take as long as
another two decades,
even though people died
in about a quarter of cases.
As one critic said about how
long it takes regulators to act:
"It would probably
take the system 2 years
to ban cyanide.”
Just recently,
a French drug maker was fined
nearly half a billion dollars
for fraudulently
and relentlessly promoting
its appetite-suppressing
weight-loss drug
while covering up known harms,
causing hundreds or thousands to
die from heart valve problems.
At least it learned its lesson,
though.
I mean, what other drug company
would conceal the harms
of appetite suppressors
after a fine that big?
After all, it was only making up
to 20 million euros a year.
Let me do the math real quick...
That’ll teach ’em!
These days, GLP-1 drug makers
are worth more
than a trillion dollars.
I’m sure they would never try
to cover anything up.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.